Turn of Huffing bomb, we saw that already
so that is one result we looked right at the
last class and you saw how we used it to manage
to bond the regret of UCB right so we will
be looking at yet another class of bandit
algorithms today right so the pack bandits
and we will be using the sheriff of ting bound
again to bound a slightly different quantity
but nevertheless of interest to remember the
Markov inequality elect people, people will
it probability theory one form of writing
it is this which is what we will need
right assuming
is positively expected.
So in the x support is in the positive range
mean so I mean whatever makes appropriate
sense for you to make sure that this is a
probability right next thing you use is the
Union bound this is
this all of you should know the probability
of the union of multiple events right this
is less than or equal to the sum of the probabilities
of the individual events that is this rather
straightforward has a fancy name called Union
bound right so whenever somebody says hope
hence by Union bound we can write this result
essentially all they are saying is that they
are upper bounding the probability of the
joint event by the sum of the probabilities
of the individual events okay these are the
results we will just keep using them as we
will do some of the proofs today.
Okay so we talked about multiple solution
concepts for bandit algorithms right so the
first one was asymptotic correctness and the
second when we talked about was regret optimality
which we already looked at one example of
a regret optimal algorithm UCB or UCB one
more correctly even though popularly when
people say UCB they refer to UCB one right
and then what is the third one pack optimality
right which was the probably approximately
correct thing where you are trying to bound
with some probability right that I mean you
are close enough to the true solution. So
that is essentially the guarantee that we
want to give right.
.
So what we look at today are PAC so the pack
bounds for multi-armed bandit problems right
well start off with a very, very simple algorithm
sort of with a very, very simple algorithm
right this is just to get you started right
it is not resorted to algorithm that you have
to use and is just to get you started so I
have an input which is I will give you an
? under d and what I am asking for is a guarantee
that at the end of this algorithm arm that
a return to you will be ? close to the optimal
armed with probability 1 minus d.
With a very high probability if when this
algorithm finishes running with a very high
probability I will give you an arm which is
? close to the true the payoff of the arm
that I give you will be ? close to the true
so if you remember the back guarantee that
we wrote right so most pack algorithm pack
style algorithms essentially take this ? and
d as inputs right and they determine some
parameters of the algorithms based on this
? and d so I am writing the algorithm in the
same style as it is in the paper that will
give you to read so that it is easy for you
to map it.
Unfortunately I will still do the online translation
of notation so that you can compare across
multiple algorithms okay, and this paper is
way, way better written than the UCB paper
so it is actually you can understand the paper
when you read it okay so this is the on the
median elimination algorithm by Eail Evanda
Shymanor and Ishai Mansoor okay, its title
action elimination for reinforcement learning
okay so the nice thing about this I can tell
you of the next things about the paper later.
But the really nice thing about the paper
is it is well written so you can easily
very simple algorithm right algorithm is very
simple algorithm what is any the log what
is l inside a log N is a number of arms right
so what did I say I change it to K rights
over here all right the last class last lecture
I change it to K yeah right is a very simple
algorithm all I am saying is take each arm
sample at some number of times okay we can
think about it right this is this is work
see if I if I get a good enough estimate for
each arm right if you get a good enough estimate
of the reward of each arm then I can say that
with a very high probability I will be ? optimal
right.
So this of course there is always a small
chance that I will go wrong right you see
what I am saying it so the idea is very simple
so I will take an arm keep pulling it many
many times right until I have gotten a good
estimate of the of the expectation right so
remember the probability with which it is
going to come up with one or whatever right
so whatever is my expectation parameter I
will just keep pulling them multiple times
until I get a good estimate of the expectation
I will do that for each of the arms that I
have right.
And once I have a good enough estimate of
the expectation all I have to do is now go
and play the arm that has the highest expectation
right that is essentially what I am doing
here now the magic here is in that number
which I have written down there right I mean
given K ? and ? that is actually a number
okay remember I take ? and everything as inputs
given all of this is actually it is actually
a number right so that magic number how did
I produce somewhere I all of this I wrote
all of these things so that you know that
you are going to use them to produce that
magic number so it is very simple.
.
So let us make things a little formal so we
call this algorithm new so then algorithm
name which takes as input ? d is an ? d pack
algorithm remember whatever what is ? d pack
we defined it in the earlier lecture right
? d pack gives you that whatever guarantees
you are talking about right ? d pack algorithm
with arm sample complexity this is the number
of times you pull the arms given by or of
n by ? squared into log N/d right so this
part is obvious and I pull each arm 1 by ? square
times lon K/d right so for n arms I have to
do that n times so my overall sample complexity
is this okay, so the interesting part now
is to show that it is actually ? d pack was
it obviously
here for today's lecture if I write n by mistake
right please point it out to me.
So I will correct it to K right okay so how
do we prove it well the sample complexity
path is obvious we do not have to prove that
we just have to prove the ? d pack so for
that we will assume that let A’ P and arm
say slit we do this Q* A’ so A’ prime
is an arm which is not ? optimal write a norm
that is ? optimal is ? close to the best term
right so Q* A* is the reward corresponding
to the best top we know that right so I am
saying then I will be pick in arm A’ says
that it is at least ? away from Q* A* right.
So the Q* of A’ is at least ? away from
Q* A* right so that means it is a bad round
right so arms about more than I mean? close
to the true oh my do not care right if I select
them I am happy because my guarantee is satisfies
I really have to worry about making a mistake
which in this case is selecting a and that
is more than ? away from the true optimal
okay so basically we are looking at the event
right so this is what we want we are looking
at right so this is the case then the algorithm
will output A’ instead of A* correct.
People onboard with me on this right so if
Q A’>QA* then my algorithm will output at
least is not output a star for me to select
A’ as the best or at least this condition
has to be satisfied okay let us put it that
way right for my algorithm to output A’
as the best arm for sure this condition must
be satisfied in fact A’ has to be higher
than every other arm right only then I will
output that but at least this condition has
to be satisfied so essentially I am going
to look at the probability of this happening
all right and then we will try to bound that
right.
So people can see why we need this condition
right so if a perm has to be reported as the
west arm it has to be at least better than
A* great so that is the condition was already
we are the being little loose here okay, this
is not really the probability that yes A’
will be the best on okay but it is only looking
at some sub B vent of that it is not all the
events together but this will give me at least
a bound on the probability so that is essentially
what you are looking at this event right.
So what is happening here, let us say that
is my that is my Q*A* okay that is why and
then this gap is at least this gap is at least
?, okay so that is this is a setup that we
have now so and I am making some estimate
of Q* A’ prime which is QA’ right and
I am making some estimate of Q*A* which is
QA* so the condition I am asking is that Q’
A’ should be higher than I mean QA’ should
be higher than QA* a star.
So essentially I am saying that I should have
QA’ here QA* somewhere lower right so this
is the case I am looking at right so this
all automatically means that either QA’
has to be more than ? by two from Q* A’
it should be at least ? by more than ? /2
above our QA* should be ?/2 below Q*A* if
they are exactly ? / 2 there will be equal
I mean there won't be one above the other
nights if one is ? by two below others ? by
two above so you can think of cases where
this is actually here right so this could
be here in which case Q* is the argument Q*A*
has to be even below right it will be more
than ? away forget about ?/2 right so likewise
for cases where you are overestimating QA*.
Then this will also have to be higher than
that in which case again it will be more than
? away right so the interesting case is when
it is in between the two right then it has
to at least one of them has to be ? /2 away
from the true estimate right either as a overestimate
or as an underestimate right is it clear so
why I wrote this now, right one of these two
events has to be satisfied right I am just
taking them as independent events and summing
them up and that still be an upper bound on
the total probability I have rights and making
things simpler and simpler for mean now what
happens here it kind of in the Sherman off
space right.
So I can apply sure enough bound here so what
would be the case here e -2?2/4 x l okay,
yeah so let us do that so this will be less
than or equal to e -2?2/4 x l what about the
other term the same right it is
a symmetrical bound so there is plus ? bit
or minus ? me too it is going to be the same
right so is it clear take so now plug in this
L there so do you get so essentially what
we need to do now is adjust this yell so that
all those things get cancelled out which is
basically what we are looking for right and
you will be left with what should I be left
with.
What should you be left with what do you think
it should be left with no I want this probability
? this is the probability of making a mistake
right so it should be ? I should I be left
with ? not quite this is the probability of
me choosing one non optimal arm by mistake
what if all my arms are non optimal except
one optimal arm right everything is away from
worst case so I should have d / k or k -1
so we will take d/ k it is easier than and
so this whole thing should simplify to d x
k right so that is what I should be looking
for so what should be my l right.
So this if we plug this in what will I get
so therefore by ? square will go so I will
get 2 lon 2k/d is not quite right and what
do I get then the 2 x 2 K / ? so I will get
d base I will get d x k right is it fine I
simplify this I get d / k so now you know
how we actually come up with this magic number
L right, by actually they are having this
bound and then figuring out what else should
I plug in here so that I get the necessary
error for the probability
so that just for one A’ well as a two outside
right to ? okay.
So this is clearer this is a naïve algorithm
the analysis also is pretty simple pretty
straightforward it's all of you are happy
with this right Sophie if I give you an algorithm
with a slightly different way of selecting
actions you can all derive the complex the
L that is required basically great it turns
out that so we have produced this complexity
here right it turns out that it is almost
impossible to get rid of this 1 / ? 2 right
and log 1 / d right, so when I try to come
up with another pack algorithm right I want
to remember what I said about pack analysis.
So I will give you an ? d and now the interesting
part is telling me how you can achieve this
? d with as few samples as possible correct
so in this case I am telling you that this
is the sample complexity right and k figures
in two places you have a k /?2 and log k / d
right it turns out that this 1 /?2 and log
of 1 / d is very hard to get rid of right
but then people now come up with and can you
get rid of this k
it should depend on K why at least once right.
I have to try every am at least one so I cannot
get rid of the K also right so the only thing
I can try and minimize hear this well I can
if I and get rid of this K right so I can
try to get rid of the log k dependency right
and then have k / ?2 log 1/ d roughly I can
try to move in that direction and once I reach
there I will probably be in the left with
trying to get rid of this to hear right and
try to make the 2 2 x 3 / 2 or 1.77 or something
let me show you know how these things proceed
right so you can try to optimize the constants
but more or less this 1 / ?2 and log 1 /d
is something that will have to live with okay.